Welcome to the
World of Warcraft
Episode 1
The Warcraft
Warcraft
Sous-titrage ST' 501
Germany today still bears the
marks of its morally burdened history.
The remnants of the Berlin Wall that
divided the city during the Cold War.
The stark lines of Nazi architecture.
And now, a massive work of public art
a few hundred meters from the German parliament.
The memorial to the murdered Jews of Europe.
The genocide of six million.
For Germany's post-war generations, the insistence on human
dignity is one way of coming to terms
with the horror of the Holocaust.
My generation is still
morally responsible for the Holocaust.
And I think that's a
very important part of the Holocaust.
I think it doesn't matter if I
committed the crime or whether it was...
It doesn't even matter whether
my grandparents personally committed any crimes
or are guilty of committing such crimes.
That's irrelevant.
These were so outrageous crimes.
And they were not just committed by individuals.
They really were committed by...
By an entire society.
It was a collective crime that was committed.
That explains why I
think there's a collective responsibility.
When I was a child, we traveled,
we made a school trip to Denmark.
And children in Denmark would throw stones at
us and yell at us as Nazi kids.
You know, they were right.
Taking responsibility for the sins of past generations,
the Holocaust is a great way to live.
And I think it's a great way to live.
The Holocaust is a great way to live.
But I think it's not clear that
Kant's philosophy can make sense of it.
For Kant, we are responsible only
for the acts we freely choose.
Not for our country's past or
for the crimes of our grandparents.
Do you think this idea that you've
articulated so eloquently of identity being shaped by...
Mm-hmm.
...by the...
...by the nation, culture, history...
...could Kant make sense of it morally?
Probably not.
I think for a number of reasons.
A, because Kant did not have, I
think, a strong understanding of the psyche.
I mean, he...
...I mean, he...
You know, it's not a psychologically informed philosopher.
To some extent, that's irrelevant.
I think he would consider the idea of the
sense of guilt, I think, or the sense of shame,
or the sense of inheriting something
from, you know, the generations before you.
I don't think he would have even thought about this.
But would he go even further and have
a principled reason not to attribute any moral responsibility...
Probably. It's interesting.
I mean, it's interesting when he...
I mean, he doesn't speak about this, so we can...
Right.
...we're just speculating.
But you're right.
I mean, to some extent, probably he would have
been against a generation taking responsibility from a previous one,
because he...
...somehow that would also mean that generation
is just an instrument of an earlier generation.
Okay.
But even if it's
something like this...
What's about this?
without first figuring out the meaning of the good life,
without first reflecting on the best way to live.
These days, we try to avoid bringing questions of virtue
into debates about justice and politics.
People disagree, after all, about the best way to live.
But can politics really be
neutral on moral and spiritual questions?
To explore this, we turn to
what may seem an unlikely place.
2,500 years ago, in ancient Athens,
we find a more demanding
idea of citizenship and of politics
than is familiar these days.
For Aristotle, politics was not just about maximizing GDP
or even protecting his kingdom.
It was about the individual rights.
It was about the good life.
Aristotle lived and taught in
Athens in the 4th century BC.